A Guide to the Southern Elections Fund & Julian Bond Papers 1965-1975
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Southern Elections Fund & Julian Bond Papers 1965-1975
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10907
There are 8,000 items (66 feet) in this collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Mr. Julian Bond of Washington, D.C., on 9 February 1990.
Biographical/Historical Information
THE SOUTHERN ELECTIONS FUND
The SEF was established in August 1969 as a non-profit corporation to assist in electing local and state level candidates for office in the eleven states of the old Confederacy (Alabama, Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, Texas, and Virginia). It provided technical assistance, moral support and grants ranging from $100 to $400 to slates or individual candidates, regardless of race, gender, religion, national origin or political affiliation. These grants, awarded by a bipartisan selection committee, provided financial grants-in-aid for election filing fees, campaign and office materials based on merit, campaign needs, and community support. The Fund began with a gift of $30,000 from an anonymous donor after Jack Chatfield, then working with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) in southern Georgia (and later the SEF's first director), observed much work being done to register black voters "but little or nothing available to help black candidates for minor office." 1
Governed by a board of trustees, the SEF sought private and corporate donations with the goal of building a financial base of support for Southern politics within the African-American community. In 1970 its contributions to the South Carolina campaigns of three blacks and two in Alabama led to their becoming the first blacks elected to those states' legislatures since the end of Reconstruction. Between 1970 and 1975 the SEF contributed campaign funds and technical advice to over 800 candidates, 70 percent of whom were elected to office as part of a grass roots process that changed the nature and color of Southern politics. 2
JULIAN BOND
Julian Bond, the son of Horace and Julia Bond, was born in Nashville, Tennessee, in 1940 and lived in Pennsylvania with his family until he enrolled at Morehouse College in 1957. In 1961 he married Alice Louise Clopton, a student at Spelman (they eventually had five children: Phyllis, Horace, Michael, Jeffrey, and Julia). In the same year Bond, one semester shy of graduation, abandoned his studies to focus on the civil rights movement; because of an increasingly active civic and political career he did not earn his bachelor's degree from Morehouse until 1971. He joined in the growing civil rights movement of the 1960s and participated in public protest against racial discrimination and became a founder and executive secretary of the Committee on Appeal for Human Rights at Atlanta University. Bond also founded and served as the communications director for the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee during 1961-1966 and worked on behalf of black voter registration in Alabama, Arkansas, Georgia, and Mississippi. He also was managing editor for the Atlanta Inquirer in 1964.
Elected to the Georgia House of Representatives in 1965, Bond was denied his seat in January 1966 because of his opposition to the Vietnam War; after winning a special election in November 1966 and a Supreme Court ruling that the House's refusal to seat him was unconstitutional, he was seated in 1967 and served until 1974. In 1968, as head of the Georgia Democratic Delagation at the National Democratic Convention, he was nominated for the Democratic presidential ticket but declined because he did not meet age requirements. He became a member of the SEF's board of trustees shortly after its inception in 1969 and later its chairman, 1969-1974.
Bond was elected to the Georgia Senate in 1974 representing the Fifth District and served until defeated for re-election in the 1986 primary. He became president of the Institute for Southern Studies in Durham, North Carolina in 1987; during 1990 he taught civil rights history at the University of Virginia. Divorced from Alice C. Bond in 1989, he married Pamela Sue Horowitz, a Washington, D. C., attorney, in 1990.
Julian Bond has worked in a variety of capacities for numerous organizations: the Delta Ministry Project of the National Council of Churches; the Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Fund; the Martin Luther King, Jr. Center for Social Change, the Center for Community Sharecropper's Fund (president); the Souther Regional Council; the New Democratic Coalition; the Voter Education Project; Southern Poverty Law Center (president); the NAACP; Southern Correspondents Reporting Racial Equality Wars; the Metropolitan Applied Research Center of New York (visiting fellow); and the Institute of Applied Politics (honorary trustee). His articles and political commentary appeared in numerous periodicals, and currently he is a moderator for "Black Forum," a nationally syndicated television program. He is the author of Black Candidates: Southern Campaign Experiences(Atlanta, 1969), and, A Time To Speak, A Time To Act: The Movement in Politics(New York, 1972). The recipient of numerous honorary degrees, Bond has been a distinguished visiting professor (1980-1991) at Drexel University, Harvard, and American University.
1In Series II, subseries B, Box 14, folder "Southern Office Holders Questionnaires" an article entitled "The Northern Role In Southern Political Progress," page 4, states the SEF was organized in the in the fall of 1968. Chatfield quote, Series II, subseries E, Box 14, folder "News Articles," 23 July 1971, Miami Herald, "Funds Aids Blacks as Candidates."
2Series II, subseries B, Box 8, SEF News & Notes, Vol. 1, No. 1, Spring, 1972, page 1; folder "Press Releases," Julian Bond, 29 October 1975.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, 1965-1975, consists of correspondence, mailing lists, newsletters and other printed items, photographs, slides, and miscellaneous materials originated by officers, administrators, and sponsors of the Southern Elections Fund, Inc., including professional and political correspondence of Julian Bond, civil rights leader and chairman of the SEF board of trustees. Several prominent contemporary political and civic individuals and organizations, particularly African-Americans, are represented in the collection by correspondence and printed materials.
Arrangement
Organization
The collection comprises three series:
I. Julian Bond Papers
II. Southern Elections Fund Papers
III. Miscellaneous & Oversize.
Series II contains five subseries:
Subseries A: Leadership/Administrators
Subseries B: Office files
Subseries C: Name files
Subseries D: Fund Raising
Subseries E: Campaigns & Elections.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically or alphabetically within each series. The original internal order and titles of select folders have been retained. Special items of note, usually letters of distinguished individuals (especially African-Americans) are indicated.
Contents List
- JULIAN BOND PAPERS
  There are several items of note including copies of a Martin Luther King, Jr., telegram to the Georgia legislature urging it to seat Representative-elect Bond despite his opposition to the Vietnam War (1966), and, autographed cards and photographs of Julian Bond with black California politician Willie Brown (other photographs are in Box 9, folder "Brandt Fund Raising Garden Party"). In the folders "Julian Bond letters as chairman of SEF Board of Trustees" are: a letter from him, 5 March 1973, in response to a Reverend Jesse L. Jackson (b.1941) telegram requesting civic, religious, and political leaders to attend a Chicago, Illinois, conference to organize protests against President Richard M. Nixon's budget cuts; a pledge of support of the SEF from California Congresswoman Yvonne Brathwaite Burke (b.1932), 12 March 1974, and a letter from Senator Henry M. Jackson (b.1912), who regrets being unable to attend a meeting, 11 July 1974.
  The folders "Julian Bond: Political and SEF correspondence" have letters from Percy E. Sutton (b.1920), president, borough of Manhattan, New York City, 9 November 1973, regarding his election victory; Johnny L. Ford (b. 1942), mayor of Tuskegee, Alabama, 6 November 1973; California State Senator Mervyn M. Dymally (b.1926) [later lieutenant governor and congressman], 30 January 1974, regarding employment for his assistant in Georgia; letters of Joseph Robbie (1916-1990), founder and general manager of the Miami Dolphins football team, 19 February and 11 April 1974; Senator Edward W. Brooke (b.1919), 7 January 1974; Coleman A. Young (b.1918), mayor of Detroit, 18 February 1974, concerning his election as mayor; and an electrostatic copy of a letter to Georgia Governor Jimmy Carter (b.1924) [later U. S. president], 4 March 1974, with Bond's offer of the SEF's assistance for Carter's 1974 "Democractic election efforts."
  "Letters to Julian Bond as chairman of SEF Board of Trustees" folders include a 22 March 1973 letter from Willie L. Brown, Jr. (b.1934), [later speaker of the California State Assembly], who is unable to serve on SEF board but promises his support; a 9 October 1973 letter from Harold E. Ford (b.1945), Tennessee House of Representatives (later member of U.S. Congress), regarding a "home rule" bill; letters, 15 October 1973 and 5 November 1974, from Leonard Woodcock, president, United Auto Workers (b.1911), enclosing donations to the SEF; and a letter of 29 March 1974 from Lady Bird Johnson (b.1912) [Claudia Taylor Johnson, widow of President Lyndon B. Johnson], who regrets being unable to serve on the SEF's board of trustees.
  Also present is Bond's state senate nomination certificate "to run in the November 5, 1974 general election as the Democratic Party nominee" in Georgia's 39th District.
  This series' folders are arranged chronologically in Boxes 1 and 2.
  - Martin Luther King, Jr., telegram to the Georgia legislature on behalf of representative elect Julian Bond 1966 Jan 10, 2 electrostatic copies (Box 1)
  - Autographed cards and photographs of Julian Bond 1970, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Julian Bond letters as chairman of SEF Board of Trustees 1970-1975, Carbon copies in 4 folders. (Box 1)
  - Howard Romaine new articles re: Julian Bond 1971 (Box 1)
  - Speeches of Julian Bond 1971 & 1974 (Box 1)
  - Julian Bond's political nad SEF correspondence 1972-1974 Sep, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Julian Bond: Political and SEF Correspondence 1974 Oct-1975 (Box 2)
  - Julian Bond: Miscellaneous SEF Draft Letters 1973, n.d.
  - Profile and Interview of Julian Bond 1973, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Letters to Julian Bond as chairman of SEF Board of Trustees 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Travel Schedules of Julian Bond, with fund-raising correspondence 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Julian Bond: Democratic nomination certificate, Georgia state senator, 39th district 1974 (Box 2)
  - Speaking Engagements: Julian Bond 1974-1975 (Box 2)
- SOUTHERN ELECTIONS FUND PAPERS
  Jack Chatfield was the SEF's first director (1968-1969), and his papers (Box 2) comprise one folder of correspondence. Of particular interest are a postcard, 10 June 1969, and letter, 21 September 1969, on how to solicit whites for fund raising, both from Virginia F. Durr (b.1903) and a letter, 8 July 1969, from Congresswoman Shirley Chisholm (b.1924) accepting an offer to become a member of the SEF board.
  Robert H. Mitchell was the SEF's treasurer in 1968 and interim treasurer and fund raising director during 1969. His papers (Box 2) comprise two folders of correspondence. These include a letter, 8 July 1969, from Jackie Robinson (1919-1972) regarding his possible membership on the board; an 10 October 1969 letter from John Conyers, Jr. (b.1929) discussing home rule in the District of Columbia; and a letter of 10 October 1969 from actor Paul L. Newman (b.1925) enclosing a contribution.
  Antonio Harrison was the first full-time director of the SEF (1969-1971); his correspondence comprises two folders (Box 2). Present is a form letter, 19 May 1970, signed (autopen) by Lilian S. Sandburg [Mrs. Carl Sandburg], (1883-1976) on behalf of Meharry Medical College and a 15 September 1970 "financial prospectus" of American expenditures for the Vietnam War.
  Clinton E. Deveaux, executive director from 1971 to 1972, was formerly on the staff of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference and Andrew Young's campaign finance manager in 1970. After being hired in February 1971, he relocated SEF headquarters from New York to Atlanta, Georgia "so it could be closer to the people it serves." (A few December 1971 documents describe him as the SEF president.) His eleven folders (Boxes 3 and 4) contain mostly letter carbons regarding fund raising. In the folders "Letters to Clinton Deveaux" are letters from Leonard Woodcock, regarding the Democratic Policy Council of the Democratic National Committee, 14 January 1972; a letter of 25 January 1972 from Robert S. Strauss (b.1918), soliciting Deveaux's membership in a "72 Sponsors Club,"; John Lewis (b.1940), concerning the Voter Education Project, 28 July 1972; Reverend Ralph David Abernathy (1926-1990), president, Southern Christian Leadership Conference, discussing the SCLC's 15th anniversary convention, 1 August 1972; and a letter of October 1972 from Senator Edward M. Kennedy (b.1932), regarding his Civilian Marksmanship Program amendment.
  Yancey Martin, executive director from 1973 to 1975, was formerly a special assistant and national minorities coordinator for Senator George McGovern and the Democratic National Committee. His papers (Boxes 4- 5) are concerned with fund raising and office management. Among these are 1973 reports of Muriel Mitchel Smith, director of research. The folders "Letters to Yancey Martin" include letters from George L. Brown (b.1926), Colorado state senator, 28 March and 13 April 1973; Congressman John Conyers (b.1929), 17 December 1973, on the aftermath of Coleman A. Young mayoralty campaign; Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 16 April 1973 (b.1931; later governor of Virginia); California State Senator Mervyn M. Dymally (b.1926) [later lieutenant governor and congressman], 12 November & 13 December 1973, 17 January 1974; Gen. Daniel "Chappie" James, Jr. (1920-1978) [later commander-in-chief, North American Air Defense Command], 26 November 1973; Fred David Gray, member, Alabama House of Representatives [1970-1974], November 13 & 19 1973; John Lewis, executive director, Voter Education Project, 1 February 1974, ending his association with the SEF; and, Senator George M. McGovern (b.1922), on various subjects, 6 December 1974.
  Other administrators whose papers are in this subseries include Ariel Williams, direct mail specialist (1973) and executive director (1975-?), and Fran Toliver, director of information (1975-?).
  Subseries B (Boxes 5-8) constitutes office files arranged alphabetically. These include SEF articles of incorporation (1973), board of trustee minutes and letters (including one from Shirley Chisholm (b.1924), congresswoman and educator, to Julian Bond, 7 Feb. 1973, resigning from the SEF due to burdens of her legislative duties), the Guide To The Southern Elections Fund's Personnel Policies and Procedures, the 1969 SEF organizational plan, and photographs of Sheriff Zelma Wyche, Tallaulah, Louisiana [town marshal and member of the SEF Board of Trustees], an autographed photograph of Sen. George McGovern for Yancey Martin, and photographs of McGovern, Martin, and [Harold Oliver?].
  This subseries is a particularly valuable source for correspondence. The folder "Correspondence--Early SEF" has an interesting letter from Taylor Branch (b.1947), author and civil rights historian, to Jack Chatfield, 29 June 1969, declaring his support of the SEF and black voting activities; an 8 August 1969 letter to Chatfield bearing a signed autograph endorsement of Maynard H. Jackson [later mayor of Atlanta] (b.1938), and 19 August 1969 letter of Curtis M. Graves (b.1938) black Texas state representative [1966-1977] and noted aerospace professional.
  Letters in the "Correspondence (Miscellaneous)" folders in Boxes 6-7 include:
  *John Lewis(b. 1940) Voter Education Project, 12 April 1973, resigns as an SEF trustee because of confusion between his roles in the VEP and SEF
  *William P. Robinson, Sr., member, Virginia House of Delegates, 29 May 1973 & 3 July 1973
  *Percy E. Sutton(b.1920), president, borough of Manhattan, 26 June 1973
  *Senator Hubert H. Humphrey(1911-1978) to Julian Bond, 24 May 1973, congratulating him on his appointment to the Commission on the Selection of the Vice Presidential Nominee
  *George L. Brown(b.1926), Colorado state senator, to Bond, 8 May 1973, concerning fund raising problems
  *Reverend Jesse L. Jackson(b.1941), president of PUSH, to Yancey Martin, 18 June 1973, thank-you note
  *Fran Shields, secretary to entertainer Bill Cosby (b.1937), 6 June 1973, to Bond regretting Cosby's inability to donate money to SEF
  *C. Delores Tucker(b.1927), secretary of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, 24 May 1973
  *Ralph David Abernathy(1926-1990), president, Southern Christian Leadership Conference, 7 March 1973 to Dr. D.J. Brooks re SCLC expenditures (carbon) incurred by Reverend Bernard S. Lee and 1 August 1973 letter to Yancey Martin regarding the SCLC's 16th anniversary convention
  *Walter F. Mondale(b.1928) to Martin, August 1 & 9, 1973, of his intent to assist the SEF (electrostatic copy)
  *Joseph Robbie(1916-1990), founder and general manager of the Miami Dolphins football team, as chair of the Democratic Executive Committee of Dade County [Florida] 25 August 1973
  *F. S. Farley, member of Petersburg, Virginia, city council 17 July 1973, thanking the SEF for contributions to his campaign
  *Barbara Jordan(b.1936), member of Congress, 6 July 1973, as a potential SEF trustee
  *Senator Herman Talmadge(b.1913), 4 August 1973, thanks and good wishes
  *California State Senator Mervyn M. Dymally(b.1926) 30 July 1973, about a California fund raiser for SEF
  Subseries C's (Box 8) name files are arranged alphabetically with folders for John Conyers (biographical sketch and photograph), Charles Evers (b. 1922) first Black mayor of Fayette, Alabama (May 1969), John Lewis (b. 1940) and his work with the Voter Education Project (biographical sketch and photograph), Southern Poverty Law Center (photographs of the Relf sisters, sterilized without parental notification or consent) and Mrs. Viola Hart, wrongfully evicted from her home, and, Andrew Young (b. 1932) of the Atlanta Community Relations Committee (photographs and items for his congressional campaign).
  Subseries D (Boxes 9-12) has alphabetical folders concerning SEF fund raising activities such as its reception for the southern premiere of the motion picture Claudine [23 April 1974]; the film's stars, Diahann Carroll [nominated for an Academy Award] and James Earl Jones, musical composer Curtis Mayfield, and theme music performers Gladys Knight and the Pips, appeared on the SEF's behalf at a private cocktail party. Materials of similar activities are available for the motion picture Don't Play Us Cheap, directed by noted black filmmaker and actor Melvin Van Peebles (b.1932); its world premiere was sponsored by the SEF and photographs of Peebles with SEF Executive Director Yancey Martin and SEF Vice-Chair and Congressman Andrew Young are present.
  Letters of Leonard Woodcock (president of the United Auto Workers) are in two folders, "Contributions from Unions" and "Fund Raising Responses" (3 January 1974). A Margaret Mead (1901-1978) form letter (signed in autopen), May 1970, endorsing Planned Parenthood is in the "Fund Appeals to SEF" folder. Of interest are electrostatic copies of faculty and staff directories for Morris Brown College, Clark College, and Atlanta University, Atlanta, Georgia, in the folder "Mailing Lists."
  Subseries E (Boxes 13-15) includes various alphabetical folders of materials for SEF campaign and election activities. The "Candidates Not Funded by SEF" folder contains letters of application for financial assistance from Avon Williams Rollins, candidate for the Knoxville, Tennessee, board of education, and Henrietta M. Canty, candidate for Atlanta's board of aldermen. The same is true for the folders "Louisiana" (with applications for financial assistance and a letter from sheriff's candidate Zelma C. Wyche, Tallaulah, Louisiana, enclosing list and handbills of various black candidates, 15 October 1975) and "Mississippi" (Ariel Williams letters and photocopies of The Institute of Politics in Mississippi.)
  The "Southern Office Holders Questionnaires" folder contains biographical information on black elected and appointive officials in the South. Joseph W. Mallisham's folder includes guidelines for poll watchers. Political campaigns by black Virginians are reflected in folders for William Ferguson Reid, Virginia House of Delegates (1968-1973), Arthur W. Walls of Arlington County, and Roland J. Walton of Norfolk. Also of special interest is the folder of racial violence news articles containing the chronologies "Some Race Related Deaths in the United States (1955-1965)" and "Additional Race Related Deaths in the United States Sept., 1965-June, 1966."
  These papers are in Boxes 2 to 15. Subseries A, arranged chronologically and alphabetically, contains materials pertaining to SEF administrators other than Bond. Researchers should note that much of this correspondence consists of thank-you letters to donors and there are miscellaneous scattered materials and references to the SEF leadership throughout the collection.
  - SUBSERIES A: LEADERSHIP/ADMINISTRATORS
    - Jack Chatfield Correspondence 1969 (Box 2)
    - Robert H. Mitchell Correspondence 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 2 folder)
    - Antonio L. Harrison Correspondence 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Clinton E. Deveaux
      - Clinton Deveaux: Resume and form letters 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - Letters to Clinton Deveaux 1971-1972, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Clinton Deveaux Letters 1971 Jan-Sep, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Clinton Deveaux Letters 1971 Oct-1972, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Yancey F. Martin
      - Letters to Yancey Martin 1973-1975, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Yancey Martin Letters 1973-1974 Jan, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Yancey Martin Letters 1974 Feb-1975 Jun, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Cover Letters, SEF Action Bulletin: Yancey Martin 1973 (Box 5)
      - Memoranda of Yancey Martin 1973 (Box 5)
      - Dennis Grubb to Yancey Martin 1973 (Box 5)
      - Muriel Mitchell Smith, Director of Research: Weekly Reports to Yancey Martin 1973 (Box 5)
      - Yancey Martin: Resume and miscellaneous 1973-1974, n.d. (Box 5)
      - Memoranda to Yancey Martin: Harold Oliver 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - Harold E. Oliver
      - Harold Oliver, Director of Fund Raising: Memoranda to Yancey Martin 1973 (Box 5)
      - Direct Mail Division Reports: Harold Oliver 1973-1975 (Box 5)
    - Ariel E. Williams Correspondence 1974-1976 (Box 5)
    - Fran Toliver, Director of Information: SEF Fund-raising n.d. (Box 5)
  - SUBSERIES B: OFFICE FILES
    - Apartments 1973, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Articles of Incorporation, Southern Elections Fund, Inc. 1973 (Box 5)
    - Black Newspapers in the United States 1972 (Box 5)
    - Blank Forms n.d. (Box 5)
    - Cash receipts/Disbursements 1969-1971, Bound volume (Box 6)
    - Board Members 1971, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Board of Trustees: Minutes and Letters 1971-1974 (Box 6)
    - Business cards and Office Equiptment n.d. (Box 6)
    - Catalogs 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Conference Invitations 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    - The Coolidge Company (Direct Mail) 1971-1972 (Box 6)